בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, today's דף Daf *daf* is דף ח *daf
chet*. It's good to be back. Thank you to everybody who helped
cover me while I was gone. We're in the middle of מכות
Makkos *Makkos*, מכות דף ח *Makkos daf chet*. Since I wasn't here
for the beginning I'll just say one or two very brief words
about מכות *Makkos*. Number one,
I think I've mentioned before, מכות *Makkos* is a small מסכת *maseches*.
It's only three פרקים *perakim*. So it doesn't really follow the order
because normally, as many academics have pointed out, the מסכתות *masechtos* are
organized according to the size of their number of chapters. But that
being said, it clearly is a continuation of סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*, as I
explained why in a number of ways. And you know, basically the
general assumption is again, I don't know if it's how you prove
these things, that initially it existed as a just as a part
of סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*, you know, and the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* would have had
like you know whatever fourteen or whatever, how many פרקים *perakim* did
סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* have, eleven? So it would have had fourteen פרקים *perakim*.
That being said, in some organizations it does not come immediately following
סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*, so go figure that one out.
Also interesting was at the beginning of מכות *Makkos*, it said why
does it begin with עדים זוממים *Eidim Zomemim*? And it said because
it's picking up from the משנה Mishna *mishna* in סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* that
said, you know, זוממי בת כהן ובועלה *Zomei bas kohen uvallah*, you
know, מקדימים *makdimim* whatever, you know, מקדימים לו סמיתה *makdimim lo semisa*.
And that was the last משנה Mishna. *mishna* of the second-to-last פרק
Perek *perek*. And רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, when רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says on
the first דף *daf* of מכות *Makkos*, he says yeah, that was
the last משנה Mishna. *mishna* of סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*. Which is another proof
that חלק *Chelek* is not the last chapter in סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* as
we pointed out. The end of חלק *Chelek* discusses עיר הנדחת *Ir
Nidachas*, which is הרג *Hereg*, and then the chapter before that dealt
with חנק *Chenek*, which is the final of the ארבע מיתות *Arba
Misos*. So really, the order was that חלק *Chelek* was the second-to-last
פרק *perek*, the last פרק *perek* was the thing dealing with חנק
*Chenek*, and then it ended with this issue about the זוממי בת
כהן *Zomemei bas kohen* and then led into מכות *Makkos* which is
about עדים זוממים *Eidim Zomemim*. So it's a very clear evidence, I
mean as if you needed other evidence, that our order of the
פרקים *perakim* in סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* is incorrect.
That's just in terms of that.
Conceptually, of course, what we're doing now is we're moving away from
ארבע מיתות *Arba Misos* of בית דין Beis Din *Beis Din* and
dealing with the other aspects about the functions of בית דין beis
din, *Beis Din*. So one is issues about עדות *eidus*, about what
are the standards of accepting testimony. So yes, it does start with
עדים זוממים *Eidim Zomemim*, but if you notice, the last משניות *mishnayos*
at the end of the first פרק *perek* didn't limit itself to
that. It dealt with the question about what if one of them
is פסול *pasul*, how do you combine עדים *eidim*, you know, that
are separate and do they have to be seen one another. So
it dealt, it didn't go into all the details, it sort of
mentioned in passing, you know, you can't hear through a translator, right?
So it's basically starting to deal with not punishments but procedural issues,
specifically around עדים *eidim*. But then the last משנה Mishna *mishna* dealt
with what do you call it, with the issues about somebody who
runs away to a different בית דין *Beis Din*, also nothing to
do with עדים *eidim*, and do you revisit the case. And then
the obligation to establish courts and to judge cases about capital crimes
and so on, whether in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. *Eretz Yisrael* or
in חוץ לארץ Chutz L'Aretz, *Chutz La'aretz*. How frequently does a בית
דין *Beis Din* deal with crimes of execution? So in the end
it was sort of wrapping up issues of testimony and then dealing
with the issues about execution. So the last משנה Mishnah. *mishna* of
the first פרק *perek* sort of was the end of all the
discussion about the executions of בית דין *Beis Din*, plus dealing with
testimony which is more broad, but obligations around testimony around capital crimes
is a slightly different standard than normal issues of testimony. So that
was sort of like the end of the discussion of capital crimes.
And now the remainder of מכות *Makkos* is going to deal with
the other ways in which בית דין *Beis Din* sort of does
judgment, as opposed to, no not civil, but what we would call
criminal, but things that are not money, bodily types of punishments that
are not execution. So our chapter is exile, גלות Galus. *Galus*, which
you know, I mean in a way it's in the תורה Torah.
*Torah* it's very interesting. Sort of like גלות Galus *Galus* and סוטה
*Sotah* are sort of cases in the תורה torah *Torah*, you weren't
expecting סוטה *Sotah* to be next word out of my mouth, which
sounds like things that were given until then could have been given
to like vigilante justice. And the תורה torah *Torah* is trying to
sort of like control it and bring it, you know, so rather
than have the redeemer of blood go and murder somebody or whatever,
the court, the תורה torah *Torah* is very explicit, right, the person's
protected, the ערי מקלט *Arei Miklat*, the court steps in etc. So
it's supposed to protect the person against vigilante justice, but also be
a type of a punishment or a כפרה Kapparah *kappara* if the
person actually did kill somebody but did it בשוגג *beshogeg*. So we'll
discuss when we get to סוטה *Sotah*. So that's another form of
you know way of dealing with crime that happened or whatever, sin
or whatever, that has to do with a person's like a בית
דין *Beis Din*'s involvement that's not monetary, and that's גלות galus, *Galus*
and that's this פרק *perek*. And then of course the big category,
which is the last פרק *perek*, which is lashes,
right. Then we deal with exile and then we deal with lashes
and that's all combined right all the different ways in which the
court sort of punishes again not dealing with monetary fines and punishments.
Okay so now we're in אלו הן הגולין which is about גלות.
galus. And
what do you call it? It's very bizarre this whole פרק you
know Michael was asking me before we started and I wish I
could tell you that I have the brilliant explanation that organizes all
this information but there seems to be a lot of like arbitrary
issues that are going on here. You know first is getting somebody
to the exact position where he is not so negligent that he's
not deserving of כפרה Kapparah but not so blameless that he doesn't
need the כפרה kapara doesn't need the atonement of גלות galus and
trying to get like this exact middle level like the first דף
in מכות opens up with all these things. This excludes a case
when he threw in one direction and it went in the other
okay presumably because that case he's blameless if you try to throw
this way it went another way. But then another thing excludes you
threw it at the person but you tried only throw you know
not to get to him only halfway to him and it went
the whole way. Well you know if you're not going to obligate
me when I do this direction and you're not going to obligate
me when I do that direction towards the person when are you
going to obligate me? You know? רשי Rashi says well when you
try to throw it that way and the guy happened to walk
in the way. Well there's a משנה Mishna that says that you're
exempt in that case too and the guy wasn't there to begin
with like what exactly like what's the logic behind that?
Yeah walking around. Going straight ahead. Right? The sword the knife when
he's going when he's it's...
Oh רשי rashi the קרן זויות Keren Zavis yeah just hap... well
I suppose well like I happen to have some pointy thing sticking
out right? So exactly like yeah and that's not considered to be
בפתע? Bepetta? That would be a perfect example of בפתע. Bepetta. You're
going this way and somebody else is going... So like don't ask
me. Not only that like even just sometimes like it's not even
seems to be trying to... Sometimes it just seems to be not
even trying to get to a degree of fault just very formalistic
types of issues like this issue that we're about to get to
I guess we'll see we'll see about like chopping wood and like
what's flying off is the handle is the top of the axe
flying off is the chip of wood flying off and it's like
why does this... why should it matter one way or the other
like you know? So I and then there becomes questions about well
how is this different than this other case? This case you say
is פטור Patur this case you say is חייב Chayav they look
like they're almost the exact same case. So I don't know. Okay?
That's my big answer to all of this. Like I don't know
anybody who really can figure this stuff out. It's a high degree
of specificity that doesn't always seem to have a logic and doesn't
always seem to be internally consistent. So I wish I could give
you a better answer but you know but but that's whatever that's
what you've got. I don't know if it was mentioned the other
day the whole issue about עלייה לצורך ירידה Aliyah Letzorech Yeridah ירידה
לצורך עלייה. Yeridah Letzorech Aliyah. By the way I should say the
idea about you know somebody who's going down downward motion but it's
for the sake of going up right? So this idea of like
pushing down on the rung of the
ladder or what was the other example the גמרא Gemara had?
The butcher bending down.
Oh yeah he's bending down but it's he's about to he's going
to pull it up. And so first of all that is a
phrase that is a big phrase used in חסידות Chassidus literature I
should mention was that mentioned yesterday? Okay which is you know if
somebody in terms of their religious life and and whatever so you
know you think it's always going to be you know if you're
serious about your religious life you're always striving to get to greater
heights and then something happens and like it seems like you know
you you know you stumble in some חטא Cheit in something that
you thought you had been beyond already in terms of your life
and like then you get to a level of despair how did
I get to this situation? So it talks about a ירידה לצורך
עלייה Yeridah Letzorech Aliyah a going down for the sake of going
up. Of course the funny thing is is that the conclusion of
the גמרא Gemara at least initially seemed to be that that's defined
as ירידה. Yeridah.
At the end of the סוגיא Sugya it seems to say that
that was defined as עלייה. Aliyah. So anyway that's a really interesting
question if you think about that spiritually but you know but like
anyway the one point to mention there first of all it seems
that the גמרא Gemara wasn't consistent and רשי says you know the
end of the סוגיא Sugya yesterday that if you're just pushing your
foot down right then but the but the rung stays steady then
that's that's not a ירידה Yeridah because you're full you know you
know the rung is steady the rung isn't going down but if
the rung is a little loose and the rung pushes down then
that's a ירידה. Yeridah. So funny I mean your leg is going
down so תוספות Tosafos pointed out and again I don't know if
this was mentioned yesterday that it's not that you fell and hit
the guy below it's that the rung fell. So if it's that
the rung fell so then you sort of say is the rung
going down? But the rung is going down in order for you
to go up and like you know anyway it's like you could
I'm sure come up with like twenty different ways of categorizing that
case. What if you fell and your foot was going down but
in general you were going up? Like how to define which is
the... Anyway it gets to be extremely confusing. Yes, Michael.
One other question I had and I was just a bit worried
about this is if the someone you know escapes from
let's say חוץ לארץ, ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
I don't want to get into that right now. That's off-topic. We
can talk about it later. All right, fine. All right, let's take
a look. Well, that again asserts the supremacy of the בית דין
in ארץ ישראל. Okay, the בבא Bava one would be too... Yeah,
I'm sure. Let's take a look who's writing the משנה. Mishna Let's
take a look at... So now we start with that with all
that as the introduction. Let's start with the next משנה. Mishna Bottom
of ז' עמוד ב'. Zayin Amud Beis. נשמטה הברזל מקיתו. Nishmata habarzel
mikito. Okay. נשמטה
הברזל מקיתו והרג. Nishmata habarzel mikito veharag. רבי אומר אינו גולה וחכמים
אומרים גולה. Rabbi Omer eino goleh v'chamim omrim goleh. So here you
have, right, this is the classic case in the תורה. torah It
says that somebody comes with his friend into the into the forest
to chop wood and it says ונשל הברזל מן העץ. V'nashal habarzel
min ha'etz. And the iron was let loose from the wood. Okay,
I'm just that's how I'll translate the word ונשל V'nashal for a
moment. Okay, so the question is what wood? The wood could refer
to the wooden handle and it means that the iron flew off
of the handle. Okay, the the head of the the head of
the axe. So you were chopping and you know the guy reached
back and the head of the axe flew off. Okay, although of
course, of course, right, the question is given our issue about ירידה
yerida you might have had to have gotten it to be lowering
it this way in order for it to be ירידה yerida or
going down that way. Okay, but anyway, but the head of the
axe flew off. That's so the עץ etz is the handle. Or
is it a transitive verb? And it means that it's caused from
the wood you were chopping
to fly off in a splinter would fly off. And that's a
debate of רבי Rabbi and חכמים. Chachamim. Now that could just be
okay, two ways of reading the פסוק. pasuk. You know, but interestingly
and without any explanation one says only my way of reading the
פסוק pasuk is חייב chayav and the other way is פטור. patur.
Without explaining why the other way should be less חייב chayav than
the first way. So let's take a look. נשמטה הברזל מקיתו. Nishmata
habarzel mikito. So the iron, the the the the handle, the head
of the what's it called, the head of an axe? It's got
to have a word name for it. The head of the axe,
the iron, you know, the top of the axe flew off from
its handle והרג veharag and killed. רבי אומר אינו גולה Rabbi Omer
eino goleh does not go to exile. That's not how I read
the verse. It's
a splinter, right? וחכמים אומרים גולה V'chamim omrim goleh no, you do
go into exile. מן העץ המתבקע Min ha'etz hamitpakeia if it caused
a splinter to fly off from the wood that was being chopped.
So רבי אומר גולה Rabbi Omer goleh you do go into exile.
That's how I read the verse. וחכמים אומרים אינו גולה V'chamim omrim
eino goleh you don't go into exile. And the גמרא Gemara does
not explain okay, good, you read the verse one way or the
other way, why should why is it conceptually different than how your
the other opinion reads the verse? So for the, you know, you
could come up with a logic, right? You could say that if
you read the verse that you're chopping wood, you know when you
chop wood splinters fly. You don't expect the top of it, the
of the of the thing to fly off. And that would be
a more classic מתעסק. mitassek. You know, the fact that as I
was lifting it up the head flew off and the head flew
like, you know, it's like it's completely unrelated, you know, in any
way of anticipating or whatever to my action, so it's like a
classic thing in הלכה halacha you would call מתעסק. mitassek. It's not
even defined as my act the thing that it flew off. Whereas
the splinters, I knew I was making splinters. You know, maybe I
need to expect it to fly so far, but obviously I'm more
responsible for the action. So to limit it to the case of
splinters for רבי Rabbi actually makes sense. You know, for the חכמים,
Chachamim, it's harder to understand unless they just say the reverse, that
one is a the splinters is too much negligence, you know. So
it's all a question of degree of negligence. Or you know, maybe
so I you know,
it's hard to exactly understand.
Or you could say how many people die from a splinter? Maybe
exactly.
Okay, maybe. Right. Right. But I would... Okay, could be. Anyway, one
way to describe it is degree of negligence. But the גמרא Gemara
later, the גמרא Gemara here is going to think that it might
be some formal distinction as well, as we'll see in a minute,
about כוחו koacho and כוח כוחו, koach koacho, whatever we'll see. And
also the גמרא Gemara later talks about, remember the case about the
guy pulling the bucket or lowering the bucket and then it snaps
and it goes and it kills somebody. So the גמרא Gemara later
is going to just in passing, and it's not directly dealing with
רבי Rabbi and רבנן, Rabbonan, so I'll mention it here, says that
what happens to there are two scenarios. One is that the rope
slipped out of your hand and the other is that the rope
snapped. So it says, well, the rope snapping is like the case
of the chopping wood where the handle flies off. Where you're left
with part of the object remaining in your hand. Part of the
object that you were holding remains in your hand. So the גמרא
Gemara says if the rope snaps by lowering the bucket, you would
only be חייב chayav according to now I guess for who says
the case about the top flying off? That's the חכמים. Chachamim. Right.
You'd only be חייב chayav according to the חכמים Chachamim who say
that you're חייב chayav when the handle is left in your hand.
But according to רבי, Rabbi, you'd be פטור patur because that's like
the handle being left in your hand and he exempts you.
Lowering a bucket and that the rope might be getting fraying and
might snap is completely anticipatable. But to say, oh well, since you
exempt by the case of the top of the, the head of
the axe where the handle remains in your hand, you're going to
exempt in this case where the rope snaps and the rope remains
in your hand, right? So it just all seems very arbitrary and
anyway, but at least if you just had the משנה mishna. you
could explain it based on a degree of negligence. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. תניא. Tanya. אמר להו רבי לחכמים, Amar
Lehu Rebbe L'Chachamim, רבי Rebbe said to the חכמים, Chachamim, וכי נאמר
ונשל הברזל מעצו? Ve'chi Ne'emar Ve'nashal Habarzel Mei'etzo? Does it say that
the that the
הברזל, Habarzel, you know, the head, you know, flew off from its
handle? It says עצו, Etzo, its handle. No, it doesn't say that.
לא נאמר אלא מן העץ, Lo Ne'emar Ella Min Ha'etz, from the
wood, meaning from the wood being chopped. ועוד, Ve'od, נאמר עץ למטה
ונאמר עץ למעלה. Ne'emar Etz Lematte Ve'ne'emar Etz Lemala. It says עץ
Etz below when it says that
the הברזל Habarzel caused it to fly off. And it says above
that they went into the עץ לחטוב עצים. Etz Lachtov Etzim. They
went into the forest to chop wood. So the word עץ Etz
is being used to refer to the thing being chopped. Okay, it's
very clear. It's a pretty darn good argument. Okay. So מה עץ
האמור למעלה מן העץ המתבקע, Ma Etz Amar Lemala Min Ha'etz Hamitpakei'a,
the same way when it starts with the description of the scenario
it means the thing being chopped, אף עץ האמור למטה מן העץ
המתבקע Af Etz Amar Lematte Min Ha'etz Hamitpakei'a when it speaks about
the accident it means the wood being chopped. אמר חייא בר אשי,
Amar Chiya Bar Ashi, pretty darn good argument. אמר רב, Amar Rav,
says רב, Rav, בשניהם מקרא אחד דרשו. Bishneihem Mikra Echad Darshu. They're
both trying to explain the same פסוק, Pasuk, no joke. So, ונשל
הברזל מן העץ. Ve'nashal Habarzel Min Ha'etz. רבי סבר, Rebbe Savar, יש
אם למסורת. Yesh Eim L'Masoret. You can read this the way it
is written even if it's not the classic way it's read. ונשל
Ve'nishal כתיב, ktiv, to read it in the transitive. Again, I'm not
a grammarian, but you would have to read it not ונשל Venashal
which is the קל, Kal, which means that the actual iron itself
flew off, but ונשל, Venishal, the transitive, it caused the wood to
fly off. ורבנן סברי, Ve'rabbanan Savri, יש אם למקרא. Yesh Eim Lamikra.
No, it goes by the way we read it. ונשל קרינן, Venashal
Karinan, which is the intransitive and therefore it means the iron flew
off.
רבי יש אם למסורת? Rebbe Yesh Eim L'Masoret? Really? And does רבי
Rebbe really say you go by the way it's read and not
the way it's written? דאמר רבי יצחק בר יוסף טופוס קדמאה, De'amar
Rabbi Yitzchak Bar Yosef Topos Kedama'ah, אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan,
רבי ורבי יהודה בן רועי בית שמאי ורבי שמעון ורבי עקיבא כולהו
סבירא להו יש אם למקרא. Rebbe Ve'rabbi Yehuda Ben Ro'ei, Beit Shammai
Ve'rabbi Shimon Ve'rabbi Akiva, Kulu Seviru Lehu Yesh Eim Lamikra. All these
תנאים Tanna'im say that you go by the way it's read and
not the way it's written. This is not our סוגיא, Sugya, so
we're not going to go through and show how all the תנאים
Tanna'im do this in a wide array of different דרשות. Drashot. But
anyway, the bottom line is that רבי Rebbe normally goes by the
way it's read, not the way it's written. And that should make
it an intransitive verb. So the גמרא Gemara says no, היינו דקאמר
להו ועוד. Hainu Dekamar Lehu Ve'od. No, that's why he was saying
look, anyway the word עץ Etz in this context means the thing
being chopped. Now of course, once that's true though, why was he
you know saying oh
look it's you can read it
to say ונשל? Venishal?
So what תוספות Tosafot says is since by context it's clear it
means the wood being chopped, it doesn't say עצו Etzo and it
and the word עץ Etz in this whole context is used you
know to mean the thing being chopped and not the handle, in
this case we're entitled to read it in the transitive form, not
the normally, you know, we're entitled to say יש אם למסורת. Yesh
Eim L'Masoret. We normally don't say יש אם למסורת, Yesh Eim L'Masoret,
we normally allow the normal way it's read you know to dictate
how to translate it. But given all the contextual clues here, it's
clear here that we should read it ונשל. Venishal. That's sort of
the way תוספות Tosafot combines the two.
Okay so if you hold ונשל Venishal means what?
It means transitive, it causes the wood to fly off. Okay and
ונשל Venashal means that intransitive, the iron flew off, not the iron
made something else fly off.
Okay, now ועוד אמר רב פפא, Ve'od Amar Rav Pappa, מאן דשדא
פיסא לדיקלא. Man Deshada Pissa L'dikla. Somebody threw like a clump of
dirt to a palm tree.
ואזיי תמרי וקטלו. Ve'azei Tamrei Ve'katlo. And the date flew off and
flew down and killed somebody. I don't know exactly how it kills
somebody, it must be a pretty heavy date. Okay. בתר מחלוקת דרבי
ורבנן. Bat'ar Machloket Di'Rebbe Ve'rabbanan. That's the debate of רבי Rebbe and
the רבנן. Rabbanan. Again, assuming that you were, it was an accident.
You were just having fun.
You didn't throw it at the date, you actually threw it at
the tree?
Yeah, or you threw it at a branch and you shook the
branch or you were doing target practice and you tried to hit
the branch, but you didn't expect the date to whatever to fall
off. Okay, obviously you weren't trying to kill somebody. But that's what
happened. Okay. So that's the debate of רבי Rebbe and the רבנן.
Rabbanan. Why? Because you're using one thing, the clump of dirt that
you're throwing and you make something else fly off and that other
thing kills somebody. Now again, that shows that it's totally a formalistic
issue about are you using one thing to make something else fly
off? Because if it's a question of degree of negligence, I mean,
you know, who knows exactly where that falls in degree of negligence?
But it does seem pretty similar, right? If you're throwing things at
trees, you're chopping wood, you have to be afraid that something might
fall off and you know and fly away. Okay, so the degree
of negligence is similar.
I don't know, it's
like again, it's
moving from chopping wood and I understand.
Right. So the גמרא Gemara is not really focusing at all here
on degree of negligence, although they're somewhat similar. It's really focusing on
the formal similarity of those two cases. Yes.
So you could check an axe beforehand much more easily than you
could figure out... Right.
Of course, why, of course why... Of course you could decide not
to throw things at trees, you know, but yes, okay, right, exactly.
So anyways, so the גמרא Gemara is not discussing degree of negligence.
ואמר מחלוקת רבי ורבנן. V'amar mahlokes Rebbi v'Rabbanan. פשיטא, P'shita, obviously, obvious,
this is once you're looking at the formal similarities it's clearly true.
No, מהו דתימא כי כוחו דמי קמשמע לן. Mahu d'teima ki kocho
dami kamashma lan.
I might think that this is one degree removed even from Rebbi's
case, because from Rebbi's case in the case of an axe, you're
holding onto the axe. So the splinter is your כוח, koach, is
one degree removed. It's not the thing you were handling, it's something
to which your energy transferred. Whereas here, it's two degrees removed. You
weren't holding onto the clump, so your energy transferred to the clump,
that's כוחו, kocho, and from there to the date, that's כוח כוחו.
koach kocho. So maybe because you're not holding onto the clump, maybe
that's considered more removed from you. So now we're getting another reason
to understand why the Rabbis would say you're exempt in Rebbi's case.
They might say that it's, you know, the thing is two removed
from you. Alright, and physically it's two removed.
Okay, so if you something you're handling makes something else go, then
that's considered to be not close enough to you. You have to
be somehow directly have handled the thing itself that did the, you
know, that did the murder. So Rebbi says no, one degree removed
is okay, but maybe this would be considered two degrees removed. So
the Gemara says, so קמשמע לן kamashma lan that it's not. אלא
כוח כוחו לרבי היכי משכחת לה? Ela koach kocho l'Rebbi heichi mashkachat
lah? So what would be two degrees removed for Rebbi, since here
the clump of what you're throwing is considered to be like the
axe you're handling? Okay, כגון, kegon, so it's like a Rube Goldberg
machine, add one other level. דשדי פיסא ומחי לגרמא, D'shada pisa u'machi
l'garma,
so you threw a clump of wood and it hit a, you
know, it hit the what do you call it, a branch, or
it hit the actual palm tree, ואזל גרמא ומחי לכבותא, v'azal garma
u'machi l'kabusa, and then that branch went and that
hit the clump of, hit like a neighboring clump of cluster of
dates, ואתא תמרי ואזל תמרי וקטל, v'ata tamrei v'azal tamrei v'katal, and
then that date fell from that and that date killed.
Then everyone would say you're פטור patur because that's three degrees, you
know, that's really כוח כוחו. koach kocho. The first thing you're handling
for Rebbi, even if you're no longer physically touching it, that's considered,
you know, you, and then the thing it makes fly off is
your כוח. koach. But if that thing that flew off or that
moved hit something else, that would be כוח כוחו. koach kocho. So
here one way of framing the debate is how much degrees removed
it is from you, and that might be why the Rabbis say
you're exempt in Rebbi's case, it's too removed from you. Alright and
physically it's two removed. Of course it doesn't explain why Rebbi says
you're exempt in the Rabbis' case, right, when the head of the
axe flies off, you know, that doesn't explain. Okay, let's look at
the next משנה. mishna,
הזורק אבן לרשות הרבים והרג. Hazorek even l'reshus harabbim v'harag. Somebody just
does throwing stones into רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and he's just having
a fun time, you know.
Did you know the people were there? Does it make a difference?
The גמרא Gemara will discuss that. הרי זה גולה, Harei ze goleh,
you go into גלות, galus? even though that seems to be a
case of like a high degree of negligence or whatever. ואליעזר בן
יעקב אומר, V'Eliezer ben Yaakov omer, ורבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר, v'Rebbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov omer, אם משיצא האבן מידו הוציא הלה את ראשו,
im misheyatza ha'even miyado hotzi halah es rosho, if he threw it
with throwing to a place where nobody was around and then the
stone was in midair, somebody walked into the space where you had
been throwing
it וקבלה, v'kiblah, and then that person received it, meaning it hit
that person, הרי זה פטור, harei ze patur, then you're exempt. Okay,
now you could say because then you're completely not negligent. Of course
if you're throwing in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim you're negligent even if
nobody was there, so the גמרא Gemara is going to make it
based on a more formal reason, just that the whole scenario had
to be in place when you actually were starting your act.
Okay. וזרק את האבן לחצרו והרג. V'zarak es ha'even l'chatzeiro v'harag. Now
let's say you were just throwing stuff in your own yard.
Okay. אם יש רשות לניזק ליכנס לשם, Im yesh reshus l'nizak l'hikannes
l'sham, now if the person who got hit had permission to go
there, you let people cut through your yard, you invited somebody to
your house, whatever the case might be. Kills the postman, exactly, good
example. So then גולה, goleh, then you go into exile because it
was a somebody you know had a right to be there and
you were therefore had the right degree of negligence. ואם לאו, V'im
lav, but if he shouldn't have been there, אינו גולה, eino goleh,
then you're off the hook because you because
presumably because you're not negligent. Now of course the question is, what
if you are negligent but he doesn't have a right to be
there? Meaning, you told the guy to leave, you know, there were
kids playing in your yard and you said, get out of here!
And you know, and they ignored you and they kept on playing.
And you said, well, I'm not going to stop doing what I
need to be doing, and you start you were continuing I don't
know clearing off your yard and throwing stones or whatever. You knew
they were there, they just weren't and they weren't supposed to be
allowed to and they weren't supposed to and you told them to
leave but you still knew they were there, right? So how much
is it that you had no idea, no need, or how much
is it just if they don't have a right in a sense
they're assuming responsibility and you're free, their presence cannot compromise your activities
like in your yard, you know? Now it's a little funny if
you're really doing stuff that's dangerous. But anyway, go try to go
try to make that argument in a court of law. Yeah, they
weren't supposed to be there so I kept on doing what I
was doing anyway.
Yeah, that would be negligence with children, right, because they wouldn't be
responsible for
themselves, yeah.
The question isn't "are they responsible?", the question is, "is that are
you free of responsibility because they shouldn't have been there?", you know?
But it's a good question. In my example, that's children, right? Like
how much... anyway, I don't know, I don't want to get into
it.
Okay, דתניא, detanya,
a thief breaking into a house and then he injures himself in
your
property.
Right, exactly, exactly.
פטור, patur, שנאמר shene'emar ואשר יבא את רעהו ביער, v'asher yavo es
re'ehu baya'ar, you go with your friend into the forest. מה יער
רשות לניזק ולמזיק ליכנס לשם, ma ya'ar reshus lanizak ulamazik likanes lesham,
the same way a forest both
the injurer and the injuree and the injuree, I mean whatever, the
injured and the injurer, right, have permission to go there, אף כל
רשות לניזק ולמזיק ליכנס לשם, af kol reshus lanizak ulamazik likanes lesham,
every, all things where they both have a right to be there.
If they don't have a right to be there, then you would
be exempt. ויצא חצר בעל הבית שאין רשות לניזק ליכנס לשם, veyatza
chatzar ba'al habayis she'ein reshus lanizak likanes lesham,
which excludes a case where the person does not have a right
to be there, you are exempt and and presumably even if you
know the person is there. אבא שאול אומר, Abba Shaul omer, מה
חטבת עצים רשות אף כל רשות, ma chatavas eitzim reshus af kol
reshus, he makes another דרשה drasha from the model in the Torah
about the chopping of the wood. The same way chopping of a
wood is something that is discretionary, so it only would refer to
cases where what you're doing is a discretionary act. יצא אב המכה
את בנו ורב הרודה את תלמידו, yatza av hamakeh es bno v'rav
harodeh es talmido, which excludes cases where what you're doing is considered
a מצוה. mitzvah. A father is hitting his son and a Rebbe
is hitting his student, okay, so welcome to the age of corporal
punishment. I mean, you know the פסוק pasuk in משלי, Mishlei, right,
is חושך שבטו שונא בנו, choseich shivto sonei bno, spare the rod,
spoil the child. The one who holds back the rod, you know,
is, you know, hates his child, right? So obviously they lived in
an age of corporal punishment, and therefore part of raising somebody is
to give them the right type of, you know, education, which sometimes
requires giving them, you know, hitting them. That was in the גמרא,
Gemara, in the time of חז"ל, Chazal, and therefore it was considered
part of a מצוה mitzvah of education, of חינוך chinuch and whatever.
So there when you're doing that in a מצוה mitzvah context, which
from the משנה you might say doesn't mean that we're people are
expected to or there's a sense that it's acceptable to it, might
mean that if somebody is doing it and it's in this context,
it's choosing to do this as a way of חינוך, chinuch, then
it's in a context of מצוה. mitzvah. We'll see what the גמרא
Gemara says. Anyway, in those cases where it's in a context of
a מצוה, mitzvah, ושליח בית דין, ushliach beis din, that's a more
obvious case, the בית דין, you know, officer is administering lashes and
he gives too many lashes or something happens and an accident happens,
in that case you're going to be exempt. Now, of course in
those
cases and the guy dies and the guy dies, as
a result of a copious number of lashes.
We'll see, we'll see. But in those cases anyway, the other thing
of course that makes those cases different is not just that you're
doing a מצוה, mitzvah, but you are like willfully inflicting injury on
another person, right? So even if you didn't have the exemption of
a מצוה, mitzvah, you would have said you're פטור patur because like
there's too much liability. When you're actually directly physically hitting somebody, I
mean in a way, you know, that's like, you know, that's like
too much conscious and, you know, intentional, you know, involvement to be
a case of to be a case of גלות. galus, גלות galus.
is where the whole thing was like an accident. Okay, here it's
like, you know, anyway, that's what you would have said, but, right?
Like I mean,
what would be a case where the person whatever? I mean let's
say a case where people getting into a fight, right? I mean
let's imagine this case, and somebody's beating somebody else up, whatever, and
they were into some bar fight and he accidentally hit him in
a way that caused him to die. He hit him in the
temple, it was an accident, of course he wasn't try- he was
just trying to, you know, to punch him whatever, but it winds
up that the person dies. Would that be גלות? galus. Right? Like
that's a very common s- I mean whatever, very common, but you
know a natural type of way in which somebody could die, you
know? So I mean logically I would say that's very different from
all the scenarios we've been looking at, right? You're willfully inflicting injury
on somebody else. But I could easily have said you're פטור, patur,
but this משנה sounds like the only reason you're פטור patur in
this case is because the guy was in the context of a
מצוה mitzvah context. Okay, so a lot of interesting scenarios here.
So you're saying that this משנה is implying that
if implying that if people were in a fight and somebody accidentally
died, that that would be a case of גלות, galus, right? You
know, again, you could talk about degree of negligence, but if the
degree of negligence was in the right middle category, even though he
was intentionally inflicting injury, it sounds like it would normally be a
case of גלות. galus.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, I would, I would agree, right? Yeah. I mean,
you're trying to say that what you would think is that he
shouldn't have the כפרה kapara of גלות.
He shouldn't have the כפרה of גלות, exactly. Well, yeah, exactly. Well,
I mean, we could think about that, but yeah. Okay, ורשות הרבים,
v'reshus harabbim, so the גמרא Gemara starts with the first case. How
are you חייב chayav in רשות הרבים? reshus harabbim? מזיד הוא, meizid
hu, you are, you know, willful. I mean, again, doesn't mean מזיד,
meizid, but you're close to being willful, it's high, high degree of
negligence.
אמר שמואל בר יצחק בסותר כותלו. Amar Shmuel bar Yitzchak besoseir koslo.
Okay, so now you're not just סתם stam doing it, you're knocking
down your wall. Your wall needs to be, it maybe you're even
trying to do a public service, you don't want your wall to
fall down and hit somebody, you're knocking it down, you're rebuilding it.
Right. Or well, זורק zorek in the context of doing it. Okay,
איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, the גמרא Gemara says איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu,
okay, but that doesn't free you from responsibility, you need to be,
watch what you're doing, and it's still too much negligence. בסותר כותלו
בלילה, Besoseir koslo balayla, you're doing it at night when nobody is
supposed to be there. בלילה נמי איבעי ליה לעיוני, Balayla nami ibei
lei l'iyunei, tough luck! I mean, you're throwing stones into רשות הרבים,
reshus harabbim, it's... Too high degree of negligence. So the גמרא gemara,
*Gemara* says, בסותר כותלו לאשפה *bisoter kotlo l'ashpah*. No, you're knocking it
in, next to is not exactly רשות הרבים *reshus harabbim*. We call
it רשות הרבים *reshus harabbim* but really what it is, is it's
like a dump. It's like a place like an abandoned yard. It's
funny that it's called a רשות הרבים *reshus harabbim*. So therefore you
don't there's no reason to expect anybody to be there. So the
גמרא gemara. *Gemara* says, האי אשפה היכי דמי *hai ashpah heichi dami*?
One minute, what's the case? אי שכיחי בה רבים *ishkichi bei rabbim*,
if it's still a type of the abandoned yard that people go
into, we're back to our previous point. פושע הוא *poshea hu*, you're
negligent, which is a better word than מזיד *meizid*. It's interesting. Before
it started with מזיד *meizid*. Maybe before it thought you're so negligent
that it's like your intentional. Here you're just like a little less
but it's called still, you're too negligent. אי לא שכיחי בה רבים
*ee lo shkichi bei rabbim*, if people don't normally go there, אונס
*onus*, then you're then you're completely free from any negligence. This again,
let's this is a perfect example of trying to find that sweet
middle spot, you know, not too negligent and not too much that
it's completely a freak occurrence. So אמר רב פפא *amar Rav Papa*,
לא צריכא אלא ela, לאשפה שעשויה לפנות בה בלילה ואין עשויה לפנות
בה ביום *lo tzricha ela l'ashpah she'asuya lifanos bah balailah v'ein asuya
lifanos bah bayom*. It's a place where people go to relieve themselves
at night, but not in the daytime. And since you know that
people are there at night, because it's too public in the day,
since you know people are there at night, it means that it
should be on your radar screen that people sometimes use it, even
though what you're doing is a daytime. Once you know people use
it at night, that should put it on your radar screen. Okay,
so that gives you but because nobody normally uses it in the
day, okay, that puts the, you know, that makes you not negligent,
but it makes you not אונס *onus*. Since it was something that
should have been on your radar screen.
Okay, so ואיכא דמקרי ויתיב *v'ika d'mikrei v'yasiv* and
there are some that occasionally go do right, we switched now to
the day. And there are some that occasionally go and sit there
and use it during the day. פושע לא הויא *poshea lo havya*,
you're not פושע *poshea* דהא אין עשויה לפנות בה ביום *d'hai ein
asuya lifanos bah bayom*, normally nobody does it. Okay? ואונס נמי לא
הויא *v'onus nami lo havya* דאיכא דמקרי ויתיב *d'ika d'mikrei v'yasiv*. Since
there are people that every now and then when somebody really has
no choice they go there, that makes you just the right degree
of fault to be in this category. All right, so remove the
interesting things from that, it's still interesting because תוספות *Tosafos* points
out, it's still a place where you're doing what you're doing in
your private domain and what's happening is in the public domain. And
that's different than the case in the תורה Torah *Torah* where both
the מזיק *mazik* and the ניזק *nizak* are in the same domain.
Okay, so from that perspective, it's still interesting, but from the fact
about degree of negligence, the גמרא gemara *Gemara* very much, you know,
sort of shaped it to be exactly in that middle spot.
Right, so this is not a case where you're trying to harm
anybody, you know? Right, right, exactly. Throwing knives in the רשות הרבים
*reshus harabbim*.
Yeah, yeah, right, right, exactly.
But what about a case like let's say, you know, your drunk
driver? Like what would they what would they say about that? In
the car?
Yeah, so that totally would be פושע *poshea*. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
אומר *Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer*, תנו רבנן rabbanan *tanu rabbanan*, ומצא
umatsa *u'matza*. So this is he says, okay, you were doing it
in this way which is the perfect middle spot of negligence, okay,
and but then somebody else walked into it. Now presumably that guy,
that doesn't make you less negligent, your negligence was that you should
have expected that occasionally somebody might come there. And occasionally somebody did
come there, right, so it doesn't mean that it was a freak
occurrence, it just means that the timing was that it happened after
the stuff left your hand. So why should that make a difference?
So from it's so again, it's a very formalistic reason. ומצא matza
*u'matza*, it says ומצא את רעהו *u'matza es re'eihu*, the, you know,
the thing that you're doing, the head of the axe or the
splinter finds a person and kills them. Okay, פרט לממציא את עצמו
*prat l'mamtzi es atzmo*, to exclude a case where a person made
himself found. Okay, so you could just sort of say, you know,
that somehow since it's all ties back to your initial act, since
when your act began the person wasn't there, it's not like part
of your initial act. The other way of framing it, which might
be the same thing just said from the reverse, is phrasing ממציא
את עצמו *mamtzi es atzmo*, it's like you say the person got
himself into this accident, right? Now again, it's not a question of
fault. The fault is the same regardless. But since physically the person
walked into it, right, so you know, we say that the person
themselves basically like put themselves in that situation, we can't totally pin
it on you. Again, it's not really a question of fault but
a question of describing what happened.
But if they're in the רשות הרבים *reshus harabbim*, people are still
walking around, right?
Right, but if they were there when you did your thing, then
you did it to them as opposed to them bringing themselves into
a dangerous situation. Of course in this case, the person was completely
faultless, he wasn't no reason to expect flying rocks, you were completely
your level of negligence was the same, but somehow physically because of
the way it happened, it's described as he did it to himself
rather than you did it to him. Okay, מכאן אמר רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב *mikan amar Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov*, אם משיהצה מידו הוציא
את ראשו *im mishe'yatza miyado hotzi es rosho*, if when the stone
left your hand the guy walked into its path, okay, he stuck
his head out there, וקיבלה פטור *v'kiblah patur*, you're exempt. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just focuses on the grammar here or whatever, the
דרשה *drasha*, למימר דמצא מעיקרא משמע *l'meimar d'matza mei'ikara mashma*. מצא *matza*
means the guy was already there, and it found the person was
already there. That's the case in the פסוק passuk *pasuk*. ורמינהי
*u'reminhi*, I'll ask you on this. ומצא *u'matza*, פרט לממציא *prat l'mamtzi*.
So it speaks about if a person, you know, basically sells his
house in an עיר חומה *ir choma*, he can buy it back,
and it says if he's able to collect the money... money, it
says ומצא כדי גאולתו, he collects the money in order to redeem
it, he can redeem the house back. So the גמרא, so the
פסוק passuk. point is that it excludes a case where he actually
had the funds available at the time he sold his house. If
he had the funds available he just hadn't liquidated his assets or
whatever, you know, tough luck buddy, you're not you don't have the
right to redeem it if you already have the money available. Okay,
ומצא he finds the money, פרט למצוי prat le-matsui to exclude cases
where the money was already available. שלא ימכור ברחוק ויגאל בקרוב shelo
yimkor berachok ve-yigal be-karov that what I'll do is like this, I'll
sell my house in the nice in central Manhattan to Michael here,
he gives me the money, and then after three months I'm able
to sell some stuff down in I don't know,
Oshkosh or whatever and I finally am able to sell it and
then I go and buy it back from Michael. So I had
the funds all along, I just chose to not liquidate that and
to sell this and now whatever, I'm sorry buddy, that's just like
working out too much for your convenience. So in that case ברע
ויגאל ביפה, bera ve-yigal be-yafe, so you're not allowed to do that
if you had the assets already. So אמר רבא, amar Rava, so
what does ומצא mean? Does it mean it happened now or was
already there? הכא מעניינא דקרא והתם מעניינא דקרא. hacha me-inyana de-kra ve-hatam
me-inyana de-kra. Each one is so the answer is that each one
is explained based on the context of the פסוק. passuk התם מעניינא
דקרא hatam me-inyana de-kra ומצא דומיא דוהשיגה ידו umatsa dumya de-vehisiga yado
because it says you are finally able to
achieve getting the money together. That's the פסוק passuk והשיגה ידו ומצא
כדי גאולתו. ve-hisiga yado umatsa kedei geulato. So והשיגה ve-hisiga means until
now you couldn't get it and now you were finally able to
get it. מה השיגה ידו מהשתא ma hisiga yado me-hashta the same
way that means now you've achieved it, אף ומצא נמי מהשתא af
umatsa nami me-hashta so it means now you've discovered found the funds.
הכא מעניינא דקרא hacha me-inyana de-kra ומצא דומיא דיער umatsa dumya de-yaar
it says it finds her friend similar to it says it goes
into the forest. מה יער מידי דאיתא מעיקרא אף ומצא נמי מידי
דאיתא מעיקרא. ma yaar midi de-ita me-ikara af umatsa nami midi de-ita
me-ikara. The same way the forest was there before, it's not it's
just a weaker because it's not as clear immediately from the context.
But anyway it means that the friend was right there like it
does sort of sound like that somewhat, this whole scenario everything was
set up like this and then you did your act. Okay. So
that's the position that the guy can't walk into it. הזורק את
האבן. hazorek et ha-even. Now we go to the fact that they
both have permission
to be
there.
אמר ליה מר בר רבנן לרבא, amar leh Mar bar rabanan le-Rava,
ממאי דבכריתת עצים דרשות? mimai de-vi-chritat etzim de-rashut? How do you know
to assume that the פסוק pasuk is talking about chopping wood that
is discretionary, not a מצוה, mitzvah, and then limit it to those
cases? דילמא בכריתת עצים דסוכה dilma bi-chritat etzim de-sukkah I'll give you
maybe it's talking about a case where you're chopping wood to do
a מצוה, mitzvah, like to build a סוכה? sukkah? בכריתת עצים דמערכה
bi-chritat etzim de-ma'aracha or chopping wood for the temple, for the altar?
ואפילו הכי רחמנא לגליה ve-afilu hachi rachmana ligleh
and nevertheless Torah says he goes into exile, maybe there's no exemption
of מצוה. mitzvah. Maybe the case of the Torah was a מצוה
mitzvah case. אמר ליה כיון דאי מצא כתוב amar leh keivan de-i
matza katuv אינו חוטא. eino choteh. Since if there was already chopped
wood there's no מצוה mitzvah to chop wood for a סוכה sukkah
or to chop wood for the temple, okay? It's just what we
call a היכי תמצא, heichi timtza, right? It's just a means to
having the necessary material. The act is not a מצוה. mitzvah. So
לאו מצוה. lav mitzvah. So since if it's already chopped it's not
a מצוה mitzvah to chop new wood, הכא נמי לאו מצוה. hacha
nami lav mitzvah. Here too, so even when it's not chopped, the
chopping is just a means, it's not a מצוה mitzvah act itself.
Do we say it's not a מצוה mitzvah to build a סוכה
sukkah though?
Someone actually says: Yeah but that's building the סוכה, sukkah, that's not
getting the material. Okay,
so anyway so it's
just called a מכשיר מצוה, machshir mitzvah, right?
It's a means but it's not an act of a מצוה mitzvah
itself. So therefore the Torah's case is still a case where it's
not a מצוה mitzvah act. So איתיביה רבינא לרבא. aitiveih Ravina le-Rava.
So Ravina challenged Rava, but
let's see the cases we're contrasting it. פרט למכה בנו והרב הרודה
תלמידו ושליח בית דין. prat le-makeh beno ve-ha-rav ha-rodeh talmido u-shliach beit
din. So those cases
about using physical punishment.
לימא כיון דאילו גמיר לאו מצוה. lema keivan de-ilu gmir lav mitzvah.
One minute, there's not a מצוה mitzvah to slap around your kid,
right? It's only a means to get them to learn, if you're
trying to rabbi's trying to educate, father's trying to get him to
live a moral type of a life. But if the kid is
doing the right thing,
there's no מצוה mitzvah to use physical
force. הכא נמי לאו מצוה. hacha nami lav mitzvah. So you're saying
what we're excluding we're not excluding cases where it's a means to
a מצוה. mitzvah. We're only what we're excluding is cases where it's
a מצוה mitzvah act per se. You hitting your kid isn't a
מצוה mitzvah act per se, it's just a means, right? Pretty good
question. So הגמרא ha-gemara says, so this is the real troubling part
of
the
גמרא.
Right, well שפטייא *Shivtaya*
he was doing a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* in terms of giving the
lashes.
No, but the guy ran and became into,
okay, we'll see about whether we're talking about extra lashes or not,
but anyway, certainly the beginning was a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*. יסר בנך
ויניחך ויתן מעדנים לנפשך *Yasser bincha viyenichacha viyiten ma'adanim linafshecha*, you know,
remonstrate your child and he will give you pleasure and you will
give, you know, delicacies to your soul.
So basically, you know, what I remember I once had a professor
who said that he didn't say he did this, but he says
he's tempted once to just go and hit my kid, I'll slap
my kid for no reason, he'll say why did you do that
and I'll say just to show you that sometimes even the righteous
suffer.
Cause you know the way we raise kids, they expect the world
to be just, but the world isn't just anyway. So it's like,
you know, somehow there's some educational benefit of showing some, you know,
strictness even if it's, even if the kid is doing everything right.
Now go ahead and explain the logic behind that. I mean, I
guess you can understand a certain mentality, you know, about that. But
anyway, it's very funny that it calls this intrinsically a מצוה mitzvah
*mitzvah*.
But that's just a father and his son maybe, because like you
know you want to educate him, but also the רב *rav* and
the תלמיד *talmid* just to like hit him because?
There's an intrinsic educational benefit apparently. I can't explain it, it's a
deeply disturbing גמרא *Gemara*.
Okay because when you're saying chastise your son?
Well how else is it going to lead to the guy dying?
Oh you mean in the פסוק *pasuk*?
Yeah in the פסוק *pasuk*.
In the פסוק *pasuk* doesn't have to be, no. Okay הדר אמרה
רבא rava, *Hadar amrah Rava*,
so thankfully the גמרא *Gemara* abandons this, לאו מלתא היא lav milsa
hi, *lav milsa hi*. No no, forget what I just said. Okay,
it's not contrasting the father hitting with the chopping wood because maybe
we'll say both of those are just a means, they're not an
intrinsic מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, and the same way one could be a
means for getting wood for a סוכה *sukkah*, this also is a
means and nothing intrinsically valuable. So then how do we exclude one?
So no, ואשר יבא את רעהו ביער *va'asher yavo es re'eihu baya'ar*.
No no, the דרשה *drasha* is not just of course chopping wood
is never a מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah*. No, sometimes it's a means of
a מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* the same way hitting a kid and so
that's not the point, but it's because of the phrasing, we know
we're dealing with purely discretionary types of chopping wood. How do you
know that? It says somebody who comes with his friend ואשר יבא
*va'asher yavo* that happens to come, דבעי עייל ודבעי לא עייל *d'ba'i
ayil vd'ba'i lo ayil*, that you can choose whether to go or
not, and not a case where you had to chop wood. דאי
סלקת דעתך דמצוה *di'salkat daita d'mitzvah*, and if we're talking about a
case like chopping wood for a סוכה *sukkah*, מי סגי דלא עייל
*mi sagi d'lo ayil*, then you had to go. So אין הכי
נמי *in hachinami*, okay yes we don't have to say that hitting
a kid is an intrinsic מצוה mitzvah? *mitzvah*, okay and
but anyway the case of the תורה *Torah* is not even that
you're doing it for like a סוכה *sukkah* purpose, okay so it's
complete discretionary. So אמר ליה amar lei רב אדא בר אהבה לרבא
*Amar lei Rav Adda bar Ahava le'Rava*, כל היכא דכתיב אשר דבעי
הוא *kol heicha d'ksiv asher d'ba'i hu*, what do you mean every
time it says אשר *asher* it means that it's some discretion? אלא
מעתה ואיש אשר יטמא ולא יתחטא *Ela me'ata vi'ish asher yitma velo
yitchata*, a person who happens to become טמא *tamei* and doesn't get
cleanse himself and then he goes into the temple he gets כרת
*kares*, right? So it says so that sounds like he got טמא
*tamei* by chance, דבעי מיטמי ודבעי לא מיטמי *d'ba'i mitamei vd'ba'i lo
mitamei*, and that's the case where he gets כרת *kares* for going
into the temple. So let's say somebody got טמא *tamei* not by
chance, not by discretionary choice. מת מצוה mitzvah דלא סגי דלא מיטמי
*Meis mitzvah d'lo sagi d'lo mitamei*, הכי נמי דפטור *hachi nami d'patur*?
If somebody had to bury a body that nobody else was burying,
he had a מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* to do it, so that's not
he happened to become טמא *tamei*, he had an obligation to become
טמא *tamei*. So would you say that that person would be exempt
if they went into the temple? The תורה *Torah* is only talking
about a case where they became טמא *tamei* out of a discretionary
choice? No, שאני התם דאמר קרא *shani asom d'amar kra*, there there's
an extra verse, it says we're talking about no matter how the
person became טמא *tamei*. It says טמא יהיה *tamei yihyeh*, he will
be טמא *tamei*. However he became טמא *tamei*, this הלכה *halacha* applies
to him. So גמרא *Gemara* says מכל מקום ההוא מיבעי ליה *mikol
makom hahu mibaya lei*, what if מכל מקום *mikol makom* whatever that
happened? So גמרא *Gemara* says no, you can't say יהיה *yihyeh* includes
even non-discretionary cases, ההוא מיבעי ליה לכדי תניא *hahu mibaya lei l'chidi
tanya*, you need it for what we teach in the ברייתא braisa,
*brayta*. טמא יהיה *Tamei yihyeh*, he shall be טמא *tamei*, לרבות טבול
יום *l'rabos tvul yom*, even somebody who went to the מקוה *mikvah*
that day and it hasn't even been night since, he still has
the remnants of the טומאה *tumah* on him, the person gets כרת
*kares*. עוד טומאתו בו *Od tumaso bo*, the טומאה *tumah* still cleaves
to him, לרבות מחוסר כפורים *l'rabos mechusar kippurim*, even if they're just
waiting to bring the קרבן *korban* to finish the טהרה *tahara* process,
they're still they're still considered טמא *tamei* and they get כרת *kares*.
So still, where do you see those are what those words include
and where do you see to include a case where it was
a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* to become טמא *tamei*? So אמר ליה אנא
מעוד קמינא *Amar lei ana m'od kamina*, no, because it says עוד
טומאתו בו *od tumaso bo*, still, so the עוד *od* is coming
to say even in a case... I still say the word אשר
*asher* means it was discretionary, but that case is talking even when
it was a מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah* to become טמא *tamei* from the
extra word עוד *od*. Okay, so that's what he learns it out.
אשר *Asher* says discretionary and we can drop the idea that hitting
a kid is an intrinsic מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah*. Okay, איכא דמתני להא
*ika d'matni la ha*, some have this whole discussion about רשות *rishus*
versus מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* not starting on our משנה *mishna* but on
the following discussion. בחמשה וחצי עשר *Bachamisha vechatzi asar*... תשבות, right, it
says six days you shall work, on the seventh day you shall
rest, in the חריש, charish, the furrowing, wait, is that the word?
Plowing. Plowing and in the harvesting you shall rest. So the simple
sense of the פסוק is talking about שבת. shabbos. But חז"ל chazal
understand that it's talking about שביעית shvi'is because you know, the emphasis
on the agriculture. So רבי עקיבא אומר,
rabbi
akiva
omer, אין צריך לומר חריש של שביעית וקציר של שביעית, ein tzarich
lomar charish shel shvi'is vekatzir shel shvi'is,
we're not talking about the plowing on שמיטה shmita itself or the
harvesting after, excuse me on שמיטה shmita itself, שכבר נאמר שדך לא
תזרע וכרמך לא
תזמור, shekevar ne'emar sadcha lo tizra vecharmecha lo tizmor, already says not
to harvest. Of course it tells us points out it doesn't say
not to plow, but okay. אלא, אפילו חריש של ערב שביעית afilu
charish shel erev shvi'is is coming to include the idea of תוספת
שביעית, tosefes shvi'is, to add on time to the like the same
way you add on time before שבת shabbos and after שבת, shabbos,
more significantly before שבת, shabbos, here too to add on time before
and after שביעית. shvi'is. חריש של ערב שביעית שנכנס לשביעית, charish shel
erev shvi'is shenichnas lashvi'is,
that you can't plow leading in right before ראש השנה rosh hashana
whatever if it's in order
to Is it a דאורייתא? de'raisa?
He understands a מצוה mitzvah right well yeah, I mean yes. I
don't want to get into the exact parameters, but yeah, he understands
that there's a דאורייתא de'raisa aspect of תוספת. tosefes. Okay, how you
know how long is it? Maybe דאורייתא de'raisa is only one minute,
you know who knows exactly. Okay, but don't plow ערב שביעית erev
shvi'is leading into שמיטה shmita for the purposes of שמיטה. shmita. ושל
מוצאי שביעית veshel motzai shvi'is וקציר של שביעית שיצא למוצאי שביעית vekatzir
shel shvi'is sheyatza lemotzai shvi'is and
harvesting the fruit after שמיטה shmita that's also a problem. Now רש"י
says one minute, it's not a problem to harvest stuff that grew
on שמיטה shmita after שמיטה, shmita, you're allowed to harvest it. Okay,
all that means is is that the stuff that grew on שמיטה
shmita retains its שמיטה shmita sanctity, retains its שמיטה shmita status after
שמיטה shmita is over. So it's a little different. Beforehand it's about,
you know, actually extending the prohibitions to the lead up period because
the lead up period, you know, helps the שמיטה shmita growth itself.
Afterwards it's about retaining the קדושה. kedusha. Anyway, that's what רבי עקיבא
rabbi akiva says. רבי ישמעאל אומר, rabbi yishmael omer, and here's where
it's relevant for us, מה חריש רשות אף קציר רשות. ma charish
reshus af katzir reshus. No no no. What the תורה is telling
you, it is talking about שבת, shabbos, it's not talking about שביעית,
shvi'is, and it's saying that what is prohibited on שבת shabbos is
discretionary acts. Okay, plowing, there's never a מצוה mitzvah. to plow. So
the same way the plowing that's prohibited is when there's it's a
non-מצווה mitzvah plowing, the harvesting that's prohibited on שבת shabbos is a
non-מצווה mitzvah harvesting. But if it's a מצוה mitzvah harvesting, it's מותר
mutar on שבת. shabbos. What's that case? יצא קציר העומר שהוא מצוה,
yatza katzir haomer shehu mitzvah, you're allowed to harvest the grain for
bringing the עומר omer on שבת shabbos that is a מצוה mitzvah
harvesting. Okay, so that's what he learns out because you never have
a plowing that's a מצוה, mitzvah so only discretionary plowing and harvesting
is אסור assur on שבת. shabbos. אמר ליה ההוא מרבנן לרבא, amar
lei hahu merabbanan lerava, so that was the משנה. So one of
the רבנן rabbanan said or ברייתא, one of the רבנן said to
רבא, rava,
ומי דחרישה דרשות, vemi decharisha direshus, who told you that the harvesting
the excuse me plowing was discretionary?
דילמא דחרישה עומר דמצוה, dilma decharisha omer demitzvah, you see it's structurally
just like the previous סוגיא sugya we did. Maybe the תורה is
talking about a case where there was a plowing that was a
מצוה. mitzvah What's a plowing that was a מצוה? mitzvah Plowing in
order to plant the wheat for the עומר. omer. That's pretty far
removed. Yeah, that sounds pretty far removed. Okay, ואפילו הכי
רחמנא תשבות ve'afilu hachi rachmana tishbos and maybe you're supposed to stop
even doing מצוה mitzvah, plowing. אמר ליה no, that's not a מצוה.
mitzvah כיון דאם מצא חרוש אינו חורש, keivan de'im matza charush eino
choreish, since if you are already plowed if it's already plowed if
it's already plowed there's no מצוה mitzvah to do the act of
plowing, לאו מצוה, lav mitzvah, that's not considered מצוה, mitzvah, that's in
the discretionary category. So since the plowing is certainly discretionary, the harvesting
is discretionary. איתיביה רבינא לרבא, eseiv ravina lerava, so רבינא ravina challenged
רבא, you're telling me that if it's only a means and not
intrinsically a מצוה, mitzvah it's in the discretionary category? So one minute,
we have our משנה, יצא אב המכה בנו ורב הרודה את תלמידו
ושליח בית דין. yatza ava hamakeh beno verav harodeh es talmido ushliach
beis din. These people are exempt because they're doing מצוה mitzvah acts
from גלות. ואמאי לימא כיון דאילו גמיר לאו מצוה הכא נמי לאו
מצוה, ve'amai leima keivan de'ilu gamir lav mitzvah hacha nami lav mitzvah,
since you're saying the dividing line between whether we say the תורה
is talking about discretionary or מצוה mitzvah is that a means is
considered in the discretionary category, well this too is a means, this
isn't an intrinsic מצוה. mitzvah, If the kid is doing the right
thing, there's no מצוה mitzvah. to do it. So once again we
have no, התם אף על גב דגמיר נמי מצוה, hasam af al
gav degamir nami mitzvah, even though the guy is learning what he's
supposed to be learning, it's still a מצוה mitzvah. to give him
a slap every now and then. מצוה קא עביד, mitzvah ka avid,
דכתיב יסר בנך ויניחך. deksiv yaseir bincha veyinichaka. Okay, so that's that
troubling conclusion, but then the גמרא abandons it. הדר ביה רבא, hadar
bei rava, לאו מלתא היא, no no no, forget what I said.
Okay, it's not a מצוה mitzvah, to slap your kids, stop. Okay,
but קצירה דומיא דחרישה. katzira dumya decharisha. The way we know the
תורה is not talking about plowing, it might be true, it might
be that things that are a means are in the מצוה category
and not in the discretionary category. And that's like the case of
the hitting of
the
kid. Okay, fine, even a means
No, but it's not the same. It's not the same. מה חרישה
מצא חרוש אינו חורש Ma charisha matza charush eino choreish because at
the end of the day from the מצוה רשות mitzvah reshut language,
Rabbi Ishmael's point is that it's not necessary. Forget the, don't use
the מצוה language. It's never necessary to do a plowing. If the
stuff is already plowed, you don't have to do a plowing in
order to plant the seeds for the עומר. Omer. So when the
תורה says don't plow on שבת, Shabbat, it means plowing which is
not necessary. Okay, or a מצוה, even if sometimes it's a מצוה
context, it's not a necessary act that had to be done. אף
קצירה נמי, Af ketzira nami, one minute. So therefore only the קצירה
ketzira that you are forbidden on שבת Shabbat is קצירה ketzira that
is not necessary. But if you have a קצירה ketzira that's a
מצוה and necessary, that can be done on שבת. Shabbat. ואי סלקא
דעתך מצוה מצא קצור אינו קוצר, Ve-ee salka deitach mitzvah matza katzur
eino kotzeir,
מצוה לקצור להביא. mitzvah liktzor le-havi.
So
if you think that it's right, a מצוה, that it would apply,
wait, how do you read that ואי סלקא דעתך מצוה? ve-ee salka
deitach mitzvah? No,
oh, if you think that you're prohibited to do a מצוה cutting
on שבת, Shabbat, then that would only be if you wouldn't have
to harvest if it was already harvested. But we don't say that.
We say that there's a מצוה to do an act of harvesting
the עומר Omer even if the weed is already cut. So the
bottom line what it's saying is the line between discretionary and מצוה
could be that anything that is, that even if it's a means
to a מצוה, we could call it a מצוה. So we're not
going to call hitting the kid סתם stam an intrinsic מצוה. Fine,
that'll be a means. But it's still different than יער yaar because
יער yaar means that it was completely discretionary. That's that distinction. And
here the distinction is חרישה charisha is a type of חרישה charisha
that is, that is not necessary, as opposed to קצירת העומר ketzirat
ha-omer which is a case that's necessary. So the basic line between
them, in one case you know based on the word אשר יבוא
asher yavo is a context of sort of discretionary, and the other
case and in our case the question is a question about necessary
versus not necessary. But at least thankfully by the conclusion we don't
have to say that hitting your kid is an intrinsic מצוה, even
though the גמרא doesn't have a problem with it once it feels
that it is necessary because of the way the kid is acting.
So we'll stop there.